Okay, settle down.
Come to your breath.
Come to your breath. Be very still.
Don't move.
Please bring to mind your favorite
addiction. What addictions do you have?
The obvious ones are alcohol or drugs.
The less obvious ones are talking,
sex,
sex on the internet, the internet
itself,
food,
certain kinds of unhealthy food.
If you had to
say what was your most serious
addiction,
what is that addiction? I would define
addiction as
something that you do habitually
that is perhaps
harmful to your health or your happiness
and you can't control it. You can't stop
it. You lie to yourself. You think you
have to do it. You make up crazy reasons
why you should be doing it.
But deep down you know it's not good or
healthy for you.
And you when you're if you're really
honest with yourself, you just can't
stop.
A little bit of it may be pleasant,
but you're unable to stop at the point
where it's pleasant and you go further
and you you make yourself tired or
unhappy.
What addiction do you have? What is your
number one addiction? We all have
something.
When was the last time you
that addiction took you over an impulse
to do something that you know wasn't
really healthy?
Try to remember the last time this
addiction
laid itself out with you.
back to your breath.
Then when you're ready, open your eyes.
Okay, we have to do better on the
breaks. Okay, cuz we have a lot of stuff
to do. And uh so, okay, you have to come
back quickly. Sit down, be quiet. All
right,
I'm sorry. I also didn't finish on time.
Otherwise, we won't make it through all
the stuff we have to make it through.
Um
there's a
third meaning of nirvana. Okay, there's
a third one.
Uh van uh the the root va
can also be seen as van which means to
conquer or to win. It's still a long a
va and uh there's a book if you're
interested in Sanskrit. There was a
great scholar named uh Dwight Whitney
from Yale. He lived in the 20s I think
he taught my teacher uh and uh
who was ancient. So anyway uh he has a
book called Sanskrit Roots and it's very
beautiful by Dwight Whitney. So if
you're interested, that's the best book.
Anyway, va also means to conquer and you
see it in the English words vanquish and
invincible.
Okay? Van va meaning to conquer or to
win. All right?
Or to go beyond some problem to overcome
or to transcend uh some problem. Okay?
uh nur in that case means something bad.
Okay. To transcend something bad or to
overcome something bad. It's the third
meaning of the word nirvana. Okay.
Then the Tibetans uh a thousand years
ago they had to make a choice. Uh which
one of these three meanings would they
use? Would they translate into their
language? We're going to see this also
with the Chinese. like I think tomorrow
I'll teach you about the choices that
the Chinese made uh in their choice of
words but uh the Tibetans had to choose
among these three they chose the third
one okay they felt that was most
important for them and uh so they
translate the word nirvana as saying
you got to hold your tongue and do it in
your throat
okay It's not, it's
lea.
It's such a common word in Tibet that it
got shortened. Okay? Like don't do that,
right? Instead of do not do that. Okay?
It's in a what do you call what do you
call it? Contraction. There's a
contraction. say
so the word is so common everyone's
talking about nirvana all the time so
they just say nerve
hope I can reach nerve you know then
everybody knows what they're talking
about okay
uh
means grief
for example when a person dies when a
loved one dies uh the emotion that you
feel is called very specific
Specifically grief uh lea which is the
trans soy is the nur grief is n negative
thing and then van is dea means to
transcend it or to go beyond it. So
lea means to go beyond grief to
transcend grief. Okay.
[Music]
So now we have three different elements.
Okay. The first nirvana blowing out your
jealousy, blowing out your addictions,
blowing out your anger. Okay. Uh you see
uh I used to be addicted to ice cream. I
don't know, Stillwell maybe remembers. I
had a Tibetan doctor over at Sixth
Street and uh I don't know if it was you
or somebody else. They brought in this
huge dog bowl of ice cream, you know,
and uh I was sitting with this doctor
and I ate the whole thing and they're
they're like,
you know, and then uh I used to
translate for the Dalai Lama's two
doctors. So, you know, and then uh then
they brought me another bowl
and they were like,
you know, they're like staring at me,
you know, then they brought a third
bowl. I did like a half gallon of ice
cream sitting there. I used to do it
regularly
and uh then finally they said, "Excuse
me, you know, you're going to get sick,
you know, and I'm like, "No, I like it,
you know." And uh
so now I don't now I don't like ice
cream anymore, you know. I don't even
eat it anymore. Uh
so think of that like an addiction. You
think of an addiction and destroying an
addiction. Nirvana would be the first
meaning blow out that addiction.
Second meaning nirvan see the illusion
that's going on that causes the desire.
Okay? See the illusion that's going on
that causes the desire. There's some
web being woven behind the desire. Okay.
You don't get good taste and good
feeling of of the things you enjoy to
eat by eating them. You you enjoy the
things you most enjoy to eat and drink
because you share them with others.
Okay? The seeds for true enjoyment of
ice cream or a cocktail or anything
else. The seeds come from serving others
and providing things to others. You see,
if you like ice cream or you want to
have that hit that you get from an
addiction, right? Whether there's sex,
uh attention, emails, if you want that
hit,
it doesn't come from consuming. It comes
from sharing. It's very interesting.
Then sooner or later you can get the hit
without the stuff.
Okay. I get the same uh feeling now
uh from a date or from you know I mean a
you know uh
and uh
so it's not coming from uh
it's not coming from the ice cream. It's
coming from sharing. Okay. And the web,
the illusion is to believe that
consuming the ice cream is what brings
you the pleasure. And it's not true.
Okay. It's not to uh deny the pleasure.
The pleasure is real. And the pleasure
is desirable. And you have a right to
your pleasures that don't hurt other
people, right? You have a right to those
pleasures. You should you should have
pleasures, right? But you don't get them
by consuming the ice cream. You get them
by serving ice cream to others. Okay.
The hit will come
uh predictably, constantly all day long.
Not by consuming the ice cream, but by
assuring that others have their wishes
fulfilled. You see, it's very beautiful.
Okay? Then then you have destroyed the
web of illusion. Okay? You got to the
non you got the kick from ice cream. You
got to the point where you got the kick
from ice cream without the ice cream.
Okay, that's nirvana, right? You blew
out your old desire.
How? You you destroyed the web, the
illusion about the ice cream. What's the
illusion? That the kick from the ice
cream is coming from the ice cream. It's
not. And the more you consume ice cream
to get that kick, the less kick you will
get. Because consuming it isn't what
gives you the kick. It's sharing it.
It's providing others what they enjoy is
what really gives you the kick and you
can skip the ice cream after a while.
You don't need it anymore and you get
the same kick. Okay? That's uh
destroying the web with regard to the
ice cream and blowing out your desire
for ice cream. Got it? Then that takes
you beyond grief.
Third meaning of nirvana. Okay. That
takes you beyond grief. What do you mean
grief? Grief here. So, I'm going to give
you like 12 meanings of grief. All
right? I'm going to give you grief. Uh,
I'm going to give you the 12 meanings of
grief. But grief here is basically the
whole exercise of trying to acquire the
ice cream to get the kick is grief.
Okay? Misunderstanding the ice cream and
trying to get it for yourself.
You know, like making sure you get a
bowl and not thinking about the person
who might not get a bowl later, right?
Eating three bowls
when other people might enjoy some. Uh
this is diluted. It doesn't work. It
isn't the consumption of the ice cream
that gives you the good feeling. It's
having shared it in the past. And the
ice cream is just a vehicle. Okay. But
misunderstanding
where the pleasure comes from, we seek
our pleasures
for ourselves at the expense of others.
See what I mean? We take three bowls to
have more pleasure and we deny someone
else a bowl, right? Who comes to the
refrigerator later, right? And then we
cause ourselves trouble. To go buy ice
cream is is trouble. to worry about is
someone else eating the ice cream, will
I have ice cream when I get home tonight
from this talk, you know, or or is the
fact that I'm out tonight going to make
my ice cream disappear? You see what I
mean? Like all the anxiety
that builds up about the acquisition and
protection of ice cream
uh is canceled. I don't have either
worry anymore. See, I don't have to go
to the store to acquire ice cream. I
don't have to make money to pay for the
ice cream. And I don't have to protect
the ice cream after I acquire it because
I get the kick without the ice cream. I
get the same pleasure without the ice
cream. Okay? So, the whole grief
associated with acquiring and protecting
my ice cream is gone. I have
okay nirvana. The third meaning of
nirvana
misunderstanding the web of illusion
causes all of our associated problems
and that's grief.
Once you realize that your screaming
boss is coming from you,
you can shut him up without a gun.
Okay. Uh, I have friends, they work in
the post office. The post office, they
hire ex-military people. They're
required to veterans, you know, so
they're always these terrible shootings
at post offices. And I I grab those
guys. I say, "Look, you don't have to
shoot your supervisor.
Uh, just just change the seats and they
will get transferred or they will quit
the post office or they'll have a heart
attack."
Okay, I'm just kidding. the last one.
I'm just kidding. Okay. Uh
so what we mean by grief here is all the
anxiety that's associated with trying to
to make things happen in your life.
Okay? If you understand where they come
from, you don't have any anxiety
anymore. They just come like money.
Okay? Uh, a lot of people have anxiety
about money. They have credit card debts
or they don't know where they're going
to get their money. They have they have
things they're supposed to pay for. They
don't have enough money. If you
understand how to plant seeds,
money will come to you uncontrollably.
And you don't have to worry about it
anymore at all. You don't have to think
about it. You don't think about how much
oxygen is in this room, right? Maybe a
little.
Uh
but like you don't walk down the street
in New York and say, you know, is is he
breathing more? Is Duchon breathing too
much more than his share in the room?
Like you don't worry about that kind of
thing. Uh there's enough oxygen for
everybody. There's enough money in the
world for everybody. You just have to
know how to make it. And then there's no
anxiety. So grief in this case means all
the anxiety associated with things like
supporting yourself. It's unnecessary.
It's just cuz you don't understand where
money comes from. If you understood you
could just make it and you'd always have
enough and you could give away money all
day. It's fun. Okay. Uh the grief is
the irony of life is that that grief is
unnecessary. The anxiety is unnecessary.
If you knew what you were doing, you
wouldn't have to worry about your
finances. They would just take care of
themselves like the oxygen in the air.
And and we we're there. I'm pretty much
there. I don't It just comes and goes.
She figures out the taxes and
you know, she has all the checks and I
say, "Give him a check. Give her a
check. There's probably five people in
this room I gave checks today." And
that's all. then it just comes back
more. Okay, you just have to know how.
Okay, then what I'm trying to say is you
will go beyond grief. There will be no
anxiety. Okay, so that's the third
meaning of nirvana.
Destroy the illusion. Nirvana number
two.
It will blow out your addiction or
whatever problem you have. Nirvana
number one.
And then you will go beyond all the
anxiety associated with that kind of
life. Shortages in your life of
partners,
shortages of energy, shortages of money,
shortages of peace in the world. You can
stop all of them. Then there's no more
anxiety. You're just kind of relaxed all
the time. Okay, that's the third
nirvana. Got it.
Let's do another meditation. We don't
have a lot of time.
Please sit up straight. Close your eyes.
Fidget. Fidget desperately for 30
seconds. Fidget. Fidget. Fidget. Good.
Okay. Fidget. Yeah. Good. Good. Now
stop.
Come to your breath. Please come to your
breath.
And please bring to mind the last time
you felt overwhelmed by being too busy.
Many things
happened to me yesterday. actually got
sick, physically sick, threw up from
being too many pressures and too much to
do. So when was the last time
you felt like you were so busy, so much
to do that it was almost unbearable
many.
When was the last time
Please make a mental list of all the
things you had to do at that time that
were over. How many items?
Responsibility promises,
engagements,
duties,
commitments
in a single day. Too many.
List them.
Count.
Please come back to your breath.
Then when you're ready, open your eyes.
Got two more to go. Okay, we have two
more to go.
But uh
Okay, so in the next
20 minutes or so, we'll do those two.
But I want you to start, you know,
considering which one is most desperate.
Okay, which one is most serious? Is it
the jealousy? Is it getting upset? Is it
overwhelming yourself with too much
stuff to do? Okay. Uh is it some
addiction to food or or something else?
I want you to start considering if we
had a vote at the end of class, which
we're going to. Do you do you feel
embarrassed to
to admit what it is in front of a bunch
of other people? If you do, you don't
have to raise your hand at the end.
Okay. But we'll have a vote. I'm just
curious. We'll vote jealousy
or addictions or busyiness or Okay. So,
start thinking about who you're going to
vote for. All right.
No, because that's the one you're going
to work on this week. There will be
special yoga programs, special
meditations.
They will start tomorrow,
right? Does everybody have a list
somewhere? You got a schedule. Is it
split up for cla? No. Yeah. So,
apparently you you do you have a
schedule? Did you get that? Did
everybody get that? There are classes
going on throughout Manhattan and and uh
there's some other country called
Brooklyn and uh and uh other places. And
then uh look at the schedule and uh the
teachers are going to try to tailor that
particular class. I'm going also
tomorrow. Okay, I'm not telling you
which one. Uh but uh we're trying to do
an experiment. I saw this done in Kalia
near Punea in Lavla near Mumbai and uh
there's a hospital. It's a it's it's uh
called Kaalia Dam and it was founded by
an Indian man who was a a medical doctor
and a yogi and I was in the diamond
business. There are 2,000 diamond
dealers in downtown Mumbai. It's very
stressful, extremely stressful business.
You have to deal with the government,
you know, you have to deal with the
mafia,
etc.
And they go to Lavla to the yoga
hospital.
It's like an hour from Mumbai. And they
built a highway. The diamond people.
It's one of the only good highways in
India. They built a highway to Lama. And
you go and you get a prescription from
the yoga the yoga teacher and it tells
you you need to do this meditation, you
need these asas,
uh you should be getting this kind of
massages,
you know, uh and it's a whole organic
thing. It's very beautiful. I'd like to
start it like we won't be very good at
it this week, but maybe in a year we'll
be better at it. We can try a couple
times but ideally
there will be for example if your thing
is anger
then I don't know about you but if I do
like Bikram yoga oranga yoga I get angry
I don't know why maybe that's not
universal I I know have f I have friends
who go to bickrim and they feel happy
but for some reason they make me more
hot and I get angry you know so the idea
is if your specialty is procr
procrastination or indolence, we will
put you in an ashtanga class. And if
your problem is anger, we'll put you in
a niguma class. You see what I mean? And
we'll try to treat your gona uh or your
dosha, your personality type. And we'll
try to provide you with a meditation and
a yoga class at least for the next two
days. And then maybe we'll get more
serious about it. Maybe we can develop
it further. Maybe you guys can help me,
you know. I don't know. I'd like to do
what they do at Gabala Dam. It's the
oldest yoga center in India and it's
very beautiful and I would like to
develop something like that. You go in
and you say I have a anger problem and
then they say okay you need to do these
twists and these bends and you need to
do these inversions and you got to do
these meditations and you got to cut
these foods out of your diet. they get a
diet uh recommendation like that and
then maybe we can treat the whole person
for different uh genres of claia. Okay,
that's my hope. This this is kind of an
experimental week. It's not going to be
too too serious yet, but help me and
let's let's get it more refined as we
go. Okay. And then maybe we can be like
Kavala Dam. It's very beautiful. Like
diamond dealers go there, they're all
they're all like shaky and going crazy
and and then they come out all happy
after a week. They keep them for a week.
They keep them in the ashram. They force
them to stay and they do certain asas
and certain it's good. I like it. I
think we should do something like that.
Anyway, for specific clas okay and
niguma in her second series which we
haven't released yet, she does that. She
identifies specific asenas for specific
mental problems, okay? Like jealousy or
anger. You should be doing this twist or
that twist. Okay? So, we'll get better
at it. You're like the pioneers, okay?
In the west. Uh,
all right. Um, I'm going to give you all
the meanings that grief has been
described as in the ancient scriptures
for 2 and a half thousand years. Okay?
I'm going to give you a lot of different
meanings of grief. I put them in your
reading, okay? But I'm going to go I'm
going to go through them from your
homework. By the way, your homework
I want those of you who've been to these
classes before, you know, I want you to
do your homework with somebody else. I
want you to cheat together on the
homework. I want you to meet somebody
else in the class who you don't already
know. Okay? This is called cart blanch
for hitting hitting on people. Okay? I
require
that you approach someone else in the
class
after class tonight and say, "Would you
like to do homework at Starbucks on 86?"
Okay. just on third just other side of
third up 86th Street you know and
they'll say no I'm busy and uh then you
try the second or third person will say
yes okay and uh I want you to connect
with other people we have people here
from all over the world we have Tokians
we have Buenosarians
you know we have Serbians
I want you to uh get to know each other
because my dream is that like the
Serbian and the Tokyo
go to Buenosaris to teach it with
Corola. You see I mean the Nirvana thing
and it's happened in previous classes.
Okay. People have gone and done weird
beautiful things together in unexpected
exotic places. Okay. So I want you to do
that. Okay. I want to set that up. So, I
I I greatly prefer if you could do your
homework with somebody else. If you do,
if you're shy, come tomorrow, Nicole,
here at 7 out out in that lobby area.
There'll be homework uh cheating groups
and uh you can join one. Just sit down
and work on your homework with somebody.
Okay? Please do your homework, okay? And
please do it with somebody else. Okay?
So, come early if you have to. By the
way, I'm sorry we start at 8. It's
because this yoga center doesn't want to
lose their income of their classes up
until 8, which I appreciate, but if you
can find us a bigger space with a better
air conditioner,
uh, God bless you. And I'm we our
original intention was to move around
New York at to different yoga centers to
to to bond them together, but they all
got too small. And uh if you know of a
better one uh or any place doesn't have
to be a yoga center but happy to try
other places. Okay. All right. Here are
some meanings of grief that are on your
homework. If you come here at 7 tomorrow
uh with the teaching assistants TAs,
right? Do you want to introduce them or
have them stand up? Can the TA stand up?
Lisa, Lindsay, and Darcy, can you stand
up? That's Darcy. That's Lisa and
Lindsay. Lisa, wait. You look strange
today. There's something about you. I
think we have to sing her a song.
[Applause]
Happy birthday to you.
Happy birthday, dear Lisa.
to
[Music]
her friends are bringing the cake
tomorrow.
Somebody asked me how many students you
want, Gasha. I said 365
with different birthdays.
Uh, okay.
So, here are some different meanings of
grief. Okay, here we go. Uh, there's a
nama named Did you have any more? Okay.
Oh, so they are TAS. They'll be here
tomorrow outside at 7:00 and you can
join one of their groups and work on
your homeworks together. Okay. Uh,
there's a llama named Quicksilver who
lived about 200 years ago. He said he
gave the classic meaning of grief. He
said the feeling you have when you lose
your child when your child dies
which is there's nothing like that.
There's nothing like that kind of pain.
My brother died while my father was
still alive and I saw what he went
through and uh it's an extraordinary
kind of pain. Okay. Now I'm going to
quiz you. Okay. I'm going to give you
what
[Music]
12 kinds of grief. I'm going to ask you
to tell me if you think that's the grief
that you stop forever when you reach
Nirvana. Okay? Each grief that's been
listed in the scriptures, I'm going to
ask you if you think that is stopped
when you reach Nirvana. Okay? So, is it
the case that after you reach Nirvana,
you will never see another person die
who's dear to you? It's not the case.
Okay? Nirvana, I'm just trying to get
you to remember what Nirvana means.
Nirvana means overcoming a negative
state of mind forever. Compassion or
grief over death is a is a good state of
mind. And you don't lose that until the
day that death itself stops in this
world, which it will. Okay? But that's
at Buddhahood, right? So technically,
you don't go beyond that kind of grief
when you reach Nirvana. Here's number
two. Grief number two. Okay. So I'm
going to ask you each time do you think
that's the grief that stops at Nirvana?
Okay.
There's an early Indian commentary
called uh the pray commentary to the
praise of confession
and it says grief can be defined as
watching how the people around us in the
world are tortured by the pain of life.
Okay. The grief is
the the sadness of watching how the
people around us are tortured by life
itself. Okay. Does that stop at Nirvana?
Not really. Okay. No. I mean, in our
heart is doesn't have anger or jealousy,
but they're constantly seeing people die
around them and they see other people
suffer and it makes them sad. Okay. So,
that's a kind of grief.
It's nyangen. It's by the way, what's
the grief in Sanskrit? There was a
famous king who was beyond all grief and
his
Yeah.
Sha sh means uh grief. Okay. It's really
any Russians
dry. Uh it means to to cry until you are
dry.
Suk to be dry.
desecated comes from that. Okay. Uh
Ashoka, his name meant no more grief, no
more.
I had a retreat and in this year retreat
he wrote me a note. Will Duncan if you
got to know he's like uh Gisha is it
possible to get dehydrated from weeping?
And I'm like
that's another thing. Okay. Uh
number three, master vasabandu fourth
fourth century. Grief is part of the
painful process of getting old and
dying.
Grief is part of the process of getting
old and dying. Does that stop when you
reach nirvana? Careful.
The causes for it stop.
Okay. The causes for the aging process
stop.
Whatever causes you've already put in
motion are not stopped. Our hearts get
old and die. But but it's not because of
anything they did after they became in
our hearts. Got it? They no longer have
karma and they no longer have cllesas.
Whatever old seeds they have can still
play out. And there are stories of
arhats getting murdered. For example, uh
first Dilama lists a bunch of stories
like that. Um but they're not creating
new seeds for it. Okay. There's they've
stopped creating new seeds for that.
Okay. All right. Number four.
Master Vasabandu also said that uh
the feeling of being torn from those we
love or encountering people or
situations which we dislike can be
called grief. Meeting people you don't
want to meet and getting torn from the
people you want to be with is grief. Do
you overcome that at Nirvana?
The causes again the causes you overcome
but old karma you have can still play
itself out. Okay, you're not creating
new situations for that kind of grief
but you still have the old things. Okay.
Number five, there's a I'm sorry, master
pajn
says that grief is all of our suffering.
All the suffering that a human being
has. Okay. Does that stop when you reach
Nirvana?
No. Technically not. Okay. Uh
your heart is pure and you cannot be
upset again. But still you have your
body was still produced by older karmas
and it will play out. Okay? You will age
and you will suffer. You will have
suffering. Okay?
You don't
make new suffering and you don't possess
the truth of suffering but that's
something else that you have to sit on
that okay kalana mitra number six
uh grief is all the impurities in a
human being
impure thoughts impure actions
impure body does that stop at nirvana
the thoughts do
the actions do but not the not the
impure pieces of you that were already
produced. Okay, those stop at
enlightenment and the body turns to
light.
Right, next one.
Now we get into some descriptions by
Lord Buddha himself. Okay, these last
six.
Grief is the pain of desiring the six
objects of the senses in an ignorant
way.
For example, ice cream. Okay.
Is it wrong to enjoy ice cream?
No. Do our hearts enjoy ice cream? Yes.
I had this epiphany when I I was in
People say, "Are you are you tight with
the Dalai Lama?" I say, "Yeah."
Then they say, "Uh, so like when was the
last time you saw him?" Like, "We had
dinner together in Washington, DC." not
long ago, you know, and they're like,
"Dang, you know, how many other people
were there?" And I said, "No, like 500."
And so I was on table 37, he was on
table 98. We could almost see him. And
you know, I was like, this was some
fundraiser. There were like 500 of us at
dinner with the dilemma. And um I'm like
spying on him like everybody else in the
room. Like they're not eating exactly.
They're like waiting to see how he eats,
you know, and they brought the food out
and they put it in front of him and he's
like
and he
and he's like laughing. He's like eating
like then he had seconds, you know, and
I'm like, dang, he's enjoying the food,
you know, like he doesn't take one pee
and and go like this, you know. And uh
of all the people in the room, I think
he enjoyed the meal the most, you know.
So our hearts enjoy
okay they do have enjoyment all right
for the objects of the senses but not
ignorant enjoyment okay what would
ignorant enjoyment be
uh eating three bowls of ice cream and
not leaving any for another person would
be the ignorant enjoyment of ice cream
okay why
you won't get more okay That's dumb
enjoyment. Okay. Wise enjoyment. His
holiness calls it enlightened
self-interest would be to share the ice
cream. Leave leave a couple bowls in the
fridge for the next person. And that's
the enlightened enjoyment of ice cream.
Okay? There is an enlightened enjoyment
of ice cream. You don't have to stop
eating ice cream. Okay? I know David
life would get mad at me, but that's
okay. Uh
do you get rid of ignorant enjoyment
when you become an arab?
Yes.
Okay. So there we hit we hit what
nirvana is. Okay. They are not capable
of misunderstanding ice cream anymore.
The biggest cla that you overcome on the
day of Nirvana is misunderstanding the
ice cream. Okay, that's the final cla
and it's the source of all other cllesas
is misunderstanding the web, the weaving
of illusion. And that you stop at
Nirvana that stops at Nirvana. You will
never again misunderstand where your
yelling boss is coming from. and you
will never again be capable of getting
angry at them. Okay, that's nirvana. You
cannot reach nirvana and still have that
misunderstanding. So they are
simultaneous.
The day that you finish off, it's called
chungu chungu. The subtlest form of the
subtlest form of your misunderstandings.
You reach nirvana and you it's not it's
not possible to be upset with someone
anymore cuz you see they're coming from
you perfectly. Okay. So nirvana and the
end of avidya of misunderstanding your
world come at the same moment. It's very
beautiful. Okay. If you understand where
all this stuff is coming from, you won't
have those six clas. We got to do
another cla.
Wait, what's the next cla? Oh, you want
me to finish this? Let's go fast. Uh,
it's in your reading.
Being grief is being surrounded by
things and people that pass away from
your life. I'm going to go a little bit
over. Is that okay? Sorry.
Is that do you stop that at nirvana? Do
you never lose loved ones and things you
enjoy after you reach nirvana?
No, you still keep losing because you
still have old karmas. You're not making
new ones but you still have old ones.
Okay.
Grief is a place of ignorant liking,
ignorant disliking and the ignorance
behind them. The middle of the wheel of
life which we'll get to tomorrow maybe.
The pig, the snake, and the rooster.
Okay. The three root misunderstandings.
Do they stop at Nirvana? Yes. Do you
stop the wheel of life at Nirvana?
Yes.
Okay. You stop sanssara. You are
stopping sanssara. No more spinning of
the wheel. You are no longer
turning the wheel. Okay? We'll get to
that tomorrow. Uh, grief is pride and
all your other negative emotions. Are
those overcome at Nirvana?
Yes, that's what Nirvana is. No more
pride, no more jealousy, no more anger,
etc. Okay. All 84,000 stop at Nirvana.
Grief is a world in which there is
conflict between people.
Do you overcome that at Nirvana?
No. Okay. Our hearts are watching the
world blow itself up and they can't stop
it. Okay, I mean they will eventually
but not until they're enlightened. Okay,
last one. It is a place where we make
things into things.
Grief is a place where we make things
into things. Do you stop that at
Nirvana? Yes. Because making things into
things means
making ice cream into something that
came to you because you bought it.
Okay? Ice cream that you bought at the
store, you are creating a fantasy.
There's no such thing.
If you had not shared ice cream in the
past and you went to the store with your
money, there wouldn't be any to buy.
Okay, got it? You don't get ice cream by
money. You get it by sharing. Okay? Not
eating the last bowl. Okay, we got to go
to one more cla or else we can't have a
vote.
[Music]
And let's just skip
judging other people. Spend 10 seconds.
Okay, this is my new meditation posture.
I mean, when you were fantasizing about
that boy in high school, you weren't
like cross-legged and in what do they
call that? Chin mudra. You were leaning
back on the couch and you were like, you
had this dumb smile?
Have you judged other people in the last
few days? Do you have a problem with it?
Do you make assumptions about people
that turn out to be completely wrong and
you make a fool out of yourself
regularly?
Okay, skip that one. Uh, next one.
Procrastination.
I might call it uh, in my case, I would
call it
uh, willful mis prior prioritizing.
I know I'm supposed to be doing
something before the other thing, but I
enjoy the other thing better and I do
that first.
Do you have a problem with that?
Do you put off things that you should be
doing and that you know you should be
doing?
So actually it's like a person who reads
the cancer warning on a cigarette
package and smokes it anyway. It's
illogical. I should have done that
before that but I don't enjoy that so
much. Taxes.
Okay,
that's enough. Two more things. Okay, we
got to have our vote.
Okay, I'm going to repeat the
candidates. Okay, I'm just going to
repeat the candidates. Okay, I'm not
saying you have to vote for mine. Okay,
uh
you might want to write down a note,
okay, as it goes by. Is it jealousy?
Is that the one that ruins your day?
Okay, you take a perfectly good day. You
start off, you have a good start to the
day, everything's going well, and then
suddenly you meet George on the street
at Sarah,
you know, is that your problem?
Is it anger?
Okay. Like your relationship with your
partner is slowly dissolving because you
can't keep your temper. Okay. I think
you see anger in partnerships that you
won't see anywhere else in the world.
You will never do to your boss or to
your friends what you do to your
partner. Okay.
Addiction
is that is that the most important one?
You know, I don't know. For me, it's
like food. You know, we have we travel
together. Uh Mercy and Yingbo are my
attendants. They're partners, but the
three of us kind of have the same habit.
If you put a pizza in front of us, we
have to eat the whole thing, you know.
uh busyiness. Are you like you just
and I think typically you blame it on
other people. You know, they're giving
me stuff to do, but really you just
enjoy. It's sort of an adrenaline thing
and you get addicted to it. If you've
been in a corporate life, executives get
addicted to it. They can't be still.
They can't sit still. They need to have
more challenges, more impossible tasks.
They do it to themselves. We all do it
to ourselves. Business judging other
people.
God knows what other people are
thinking. How do you know, right? Who
knows if the guy's an opera expert or
not?
Who are you to say?
And then uh procrastination. Okay, you
you got it.
You ready to vote?
Okay, I'm not going to count. I'm just
curious. Okay, and then whoever wins
your vote, if you have time, try to go
to the yoga class or try to go to the
meditation which relates to that one.
Okay, and we'll get better at it. This
week is sort of experimental and you
know, I think we have to refine it. So,
you ready? Uh, jealousy.
Dang, I thought more people had that
problem. Now I'm jealous of all the
people who don't have it.
[Laughter]
Anger. Who votes for anger? Oh my gosh.
Okay. All right. Anger is making a good
show. Uh, addictions.
That's pretty good.
Probably just more angry than addicted.
Okay. Uh, busy busyiness.
That's New York.
All right. I don't know. They're pretty
You got to tell Nama Kimberly we we we
did pretty good. Okay. Uh, judging other
people.
Yeah. I think we all do it, but we just
don't admit it. Okay. Uh,
procrastination, mis prioritizing.
Okay, good. How many people are perfect?
[Laughter]
I get jealous of you. Okay. Uh,
okay. So, I was going to have you put it
on your name tag. I was going to give
you a name tag. He was going to say
Gushy Michael jealousy. You know, we
have green name tags. Uh
but uh let's think about it, Nicole.
It might be embarrassing. I think it's
good to be embarrassed about your worst
glacia. Then maybe you do something
about it next year. You just put
perfect, you know? Uh
okay. But keep it in mind, okay? Don't
forget who won your vote and that's
going to be the one we're going to work
on. Uh
and you will be happier by the end.
That's the whole point of having these
classes, isn't it? You know, you will be
a happier person. Last thing. Okay.
Somebody asked Lord Buddha
in the sutra of the great Nirvana. They
said, "Can you just summarize what is
Nirvana?" You know, what is your highest
position on the meaning of Nirvana? And
he said, Lord Buddha said, Nirvana is
happiness.
And that's all. Okay. If you are
practicing well, if your yoga is good,
if your meditation is good, if your
study is good.
My first lama Gishand he said the the
indication is that you feel happier day
by day. Okay. The indication that you
are practicing a spiritual path is that
you feel happier day by day. And if you
don't feel happier, you are not
practicing.
Okay? If you don't feel happier this
month than last month, and if you don't
feel happier this year than last year,
you're not practicing. Something's
wrong. Okay?
Uh if you're not happier with your life,
if you're not happier with yourself, if
you're not happier with your
relationships, if you're not happier
with your career and your work, then
you're not practicing. There's something
wrong with your practice. Okay? And you
have to fix it. So Lord Buddha defined
nirvana simply as happiness. And and I
think uh we should think about that.
Okay? I want you to be happier by the
end of this program than you are now.
Okay? And and that means we we did a
good we did the right thing. We're doing
something good. Your your life should be
increasingly happier, brighter, more
sunshine, more magic every day. And if
it's not, there's a problem. And I don't
mean you're evil or you're deficient or
you should have low selfspiritual
esteem. I I'm not saying that. I'm
saying we got to get you back on track
and it's not a big deal. Okay? Uh we're
going to work on your favorite cla and
we're going to chip away at it this
week. Okay? And I want you to be happier
in a month than you are now. That's the
whole point, isn't it? That we all
become happier and happier. Okay? That's
what Buddha said. That's your last
homework question.
All right. We're going to dedicate the
karma. Okay. Mr. Stillwell, would you
mind? Okay.
She
[Music]
no
sing.
Turn on your ship.
Thank you for coming and thank you for
giving me a chance to talk about these
holy things because it it makes me work
hard and think about them and apply them
to myself. So, I'm very grateful
for that. Um, if you don't know the
prayers at the end, don't stress about
it. Are they in the notebook? Uh, we can
give them to you, okay? And then, uh,
you don't have to worry about some
foreign language. Uh, you can just sit
there and and bathe in the in the chant.
The idea is that you are giving away the
good karma to the city of New York, to
everyone in New York. Okay? They didn't
get here.
Uh but you are sending them the good
karma you made. You are banking it.
Okay, that's the meaning of those
prayers. All right, good night. See you
tomorrow.